Retail sales
fell in July,
shocking the mainstream,
although this is a completely
predictable
result of the mini-
cycles we've
been telling you about for
the last, well, Steve, the
last couple of years,
right?  We said, "
Look, there
are artificial peaks in the calendar
."  The economy,
especially consumer
spending, looks
very good in the spring,
usually for artificial
reasons.  Last year
it was an advance
due to customs duties.  This
year it was an
energy shock.
People were spending on
gas, plus one of
Steve's favorite topics was
tax
refunds.  We
told you that once the
tax
refund money
runs out,
consumer spending
will weaken.  And that's exactly what
happened.  So,
we had another spring
that looked very
good for consumer
spending, but then,
gradually, as
spring turned into
summer, things
slowed down until
July.  Now
retail sales
are down, a
real recession.
The control group, the
control group
is also decreasing.  We had a
drop in
car sales, the
payback for that.  So what
we're seeing again
is more evidence of
these mini-cycles.
In the spring, everything looks
good, and everyone is shocked
in the summer when the data
looks worse.  And,
of course, what is behind
all this?  Behind this is the
labor market.  And
we were reminded of this
a week earlier when the
employment report
came in shockingly
negative.  And
look at the
employment numbers, they
show the same
mini-
cycle behavior.  So, Steve,
tax
refunds, mini-
cycles, artificial peaks.
Now we have
retail sales
that
are declining in July, and
quite sharply.  Yes,
there were certain islands of
strength, but they
always are, but overall
consumer spending
weakened.  I want to
say—exactly on
schedule, but that's
too loud a
term, but we
expected some
payback, and here it is.
Yes, Jeff, I
actually thought
we would see a drop in
retail sales
before it
happened.  You know, when
we look, you know,
step back and
look at the data, you're
absolutely right
about it being about the
labor market.  Because we're
not just seeing,
say, a one-time
report because
gasoline prices increased and
people cut back on
spending.  We see a
confluence of many
factors.  So the question
really is, is
this a one-time event, or is this the
start of a trend where the
mini-cycle will actually
become much
bigger?  And when we
look at the
labor market, one of my
favorite data points is
average hourly
earnings, but not
overall, but for
production and
non-management
personnel.  You know, the
average
American
worker.  And that
figure started to
drop sharply, and we can
look back at every
cycle and see that
every time it
starts to decline,
retail sales
fall.  Especially in
times of high
inflation.  So this is a
clear demand disruption,
consumers saying, "
Look, I want to
keep
spending, but I can't
afford to." The next thing
you see,
retail sales
start to fall, and
what happens?
Layoffs happen
in every cycle. So I
think this is the
start of a trend, not
just another mini-
cycle that we do
n't have to worry about.
I think we have something to
worry about.
So the mini-cycle
is moving into a more
recognizable business
cycle where people say, "
Okay, this is bad."  This
actually looks
more like a recession.  And
this is something we've
talked about before.
Income statistics,
which obviously
depend on the
labor market.  So the
labor market creates income,
and if you look
at the
income statistics, they've been getting
worse since last
fall.  You know,
the increase in spending
in the spring
has somewhat masked this
weakness because
everyone is focusing
on the spending side,
not the revenue side.
And to some extent,
you know, the
business survey had a
pretty good
month or couple of
months in March and
April, but that also
came to naught.  But it's
understandable why the mini-
cycle somewhat obscured the
underlying trend, which
, as Steve said, and I
agree with you, Steve,
has been significantly
eroded.  And we have a
few other
points to add.
Um, earnings are a
good indicator.  That's a
very good
leading
indicator, but so is the
savings rate,
right, Steve?  So while
all this
mini-cycle behavior is going on, the
deterioration in incomes
has caused
a lot of consumers (
not the ones at the
high end of the stock market, of course, but
a lot of consumers at
the bottom who are struggling with the
labor market,
jobs,
income,
perceptions of all of
that)—their
savings rates have fallen to
the areas that you
typically see before,
as Steve said, a
change in the normal
business cycle.  Because
once consumers
exhaust their
savings, as we
know, they
run out of money from
tax refunds
, the labor market is not
sustainable;  it doesn't
recover like everyone
said, again, the
same mini-cycle.
So, we are at a
crossroads: the consumer
sees that there are
no savings left,
there is no safety margin, and
the government will not come to the
rescue.  I do
n't have any investments in the
stock market because I'm
not very wealthy,
so, you know, maybe
I have a small
retirement account,
but that doesn't really
help either.  So we
really need either
the economy to start
growing in a meaningful and
sustainable way, or,
Steve, I understand your
point, the economy is not
growing, but rather, it's
falling in a meaningful and sustainable way.  Before
we continue with our
video, let me
ask you a
question.  What if
your gold could
earn you a
profit every month in the
form of more
gold?    This is exactly what the
sponsor of
today's video, Monetary
Metals, allows you to do.  Here's how it
works.  You
remain the
owner of the gold,
it is registered in your
name, fully
insured, but
instead of
just lying around doing nothing
, it starts
working for you.
Monetary Metals has created a
system that
turns passive
gold into
productive,
generating real
income in physical
gold, not dollars
.  No sales,
no trading,
no conversion.
You keep your
gold and
get
more of it every month.  It's a simple
idea, but it
solves a big
problem.  If gold
is money, it should
work like money, and
now it finally
can.  If you are a
long-term
gold owner
looking for a smarter
way to store
value, visit
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
I repeat, this is
monetary-metals.com/snyder.  I
highly
recommend
booking a call
with them today
to see if
this option is right for you
.  We thank
Monetary Metals for their
sponsorship, and now
we return to
our video.
And you know, Jeff, that's
one way
to understand that this is not an
isolated report, because
savings rates,
I think, are falling to
levels that we haven't
seen since the 1940s.  I
mean, that doesn't bode
well
.  So if we
look at where
retail sales increased,
we can see that at the
same time
savings rates
started to fall.  So
consumers said, "
Look, we're
hoping
the economy
will recover. We don't
want to cut
spending, but our
incomes are falling. The
job market is not that
great, but we
keep
spending in the hope that
it will. And our response
was, of course, we've
seen
retail sales go up.
Everyone's been trying to
get ahead of
inflation. And now that's
starting to
change, you
know, we were talking
about the minimum
inventory levels in Cushing,
Oklahoma. You know
, these minimums are
essentially the same age as the
bills that
are running out. And when
consumers start to
notice that,
they say, "
Listen. My
paycheck is going down
, my savings are
going down. The natural
reaction is you
start to
cut back on your
spending. In fact, we've
even seen
affluent consumers
start saving, and
you know, it does
n't usually happen right
away. That's one of the
delayed effects.
So this is a very
dangerous moment,
because if we
actually see that
consumers will start
prioritizing
savings,
debt repayment, and
spending cuts, then
retail sales will
plummet,
sending this mini-
cycle into what I
think will be the beginning of a
longer business
cycle that could
lead us straight
into a recession.
So, yes, that was a
big factor too. Yes
, the wealthy
. That's the
last leg of the
economy. That's the
consumer economy. The
other part of
the economy is, of course
, the AI ​​bubble
and the
AI ​​infrastructure.
But on the consumer side
—the wealthy—it's
been the main driver
of what? For
over a year now, starting,
essentially, in early
2025. Consumers who
have significant assets
in the stock market—
we talk about the "
wealth effect,"
central bankers
talk about the "
wealth effect,"
economists and the media
talk about the "
wealth effect." In this
case, it really
was. The problem is,
that it wasn't very
large. It was
concentrated
in, let's say, the top 10%,
roughly speaking. So that 10%
saw the stock
market with all its
volatility and its
ups and downs,
but they kept
spending. So if the
retail
sales numbers are right, and there's
no reason to doubt them now. I
mean, it's not like the
employer survey, which is
radically
revised from
month to month, then
it indicates,
at least in one
month, that wealthy
people can say,
"Okay, wait.
We're going to
slow down. We don't
like where things are
going. But
let me
ask you this.
The only counterargument
that I've seen in the
financial media about
retail sales
is that it has a
lot to do
with Amazon Prime Day.
And Amazon Prime Day
was in June this year, not
July, and that supposedly
creates statistical
bias or
comparability issues
.
That doesn't make any sense to me.  changes,
but maybe in
the mainstream, most
people and the comments
are like,
"Okay, it's a calendar
distortion, so a little bit of a
dip in June
or July is not that
unusual,
given the
seasonality
." Do you see
any
subtext to that, too?
You know, Jeff, I—I don't,
and I think it's
just pundits and
economists
trying to
justify this data.
It's kind of like the
nonfarm payrolls report
. Oh,
you know, it's
negative, but they
say it's not that
bad. It's a
one-time event. Oh, it's
negative again, and we
got
downward revisions. Oh, well,
you know, there comes a point
where you can't
embellish what doesn't
embellish. So
in terms of retail
sales, that's really the
last hope for
the economy, right?
Like, the labor market
is slowing, but
as long as people
keep
spending,
hiring will
pick up again. So there has to
be some kind of  natural
excuse. Why did it
go down? Oh, it's
because of Amazon. But what else did
we see? We
saw car sales go down
. People say, "
Look, I don't want to
buy a car." But
look at
energy. We
saw
gasoline consumption go down. And
now it's August, you
know, July and
August. Those are big
travel months.
But, Jeff, we
talked about this
a few months ago,
coming into
this energy
shock. So, consumers
are saying, "Look, I'm
going to take my vacation
home."  I'm canceling
flights, I'm canceling
hotels, I'm not going to
travel much." And
now it's
showing up in the
data, and nobody wants
to believe that this is actually
happening.
That's a very valid
point, which I
wrote about in our
detailed analysis
earlier this
week. First of all, Amazon,
yes. Look, if
Amazon is creating a
calendar distortion, then
the economy
is not
healthy anyway, right? Because
consumers who were supposed to
spend in
July and
spent in June
would have spent in
June and July
if the economy was
really healthy. That
doesn't create
a distortion if
the economy is really
moving forward. I do
n't believe that either. But what
you said is
also what we see in the data.
Look,
for example, at the
Energy
Information Administration, the government
agency that
tracks
energy data. They
reported that
gasoline consumption
is down. And it's
falling right now, during the
peak
travel season. Of course,  it has
n't collapsed, it's not
falling precipitously, but it's
very similar to the
labor market. The labor market is
n't collapsing either, but
it's showing a
slight decline. The thing is, the
demand for gasoline, as
you rightly pointed out,
Steve, especially in the peak
season: demand should be
constantly increasing
simply because of the
population growth
. So, the demand for
gasoline should be
increasing. You rarely
see the demand
for gasoline fall year
over year. That
only happens in—
yes, I'll use
the word that Steve already used
—a
recession. That happened
last year, but do
you remember what happened
then, this mini-cycle?
We had a weak labor market in the summer
, so right before the
peak travel season,
the demand for gasoline in
2025 was lower than it was in
2024. Here we are again in
2026. Guess what
happens?
Weak
labor market, falling
incomes, higher
energy prices,
savings have
dwindled or
dried up,
tax refunds
have run out, and what do we
see?  It's peak
travel season, and
gasoline demand is a little lower
than it was in 2025, which was
a little lower than it was in
2024. All of this tells
us, at a minimum, that
minicycles are here,
they're going to continue, but
at some point you
get to a
crossroads where you say,
"Okay, this
can't go on." So
the question that we're
really asking and
trying
to analyze is,
where is that
point? I know, we've
been asking this question for
a few years now, and it's
understandable why Jay
Powell or Kevin Warsh
can go on air and
say, "The economy is
stable because it hasn't
collapsed." That's true
, but it doesn't
eliminate the weakness
that's been there
for the last
few years, and it doesn't
eliminate the weakness that's
rearing its
head again.
You know, Joe, it's
funny, I'm trying
not to laugh, because it's
like, "Hey, how do
you know everything's
good?"  Well, it's not
broken." And this,
you know, if
you look at it from a
consumer perspective, we
see
retail sales falling,
but what have they been
enduring all this
time? You know, high
consumer prices, high
energy prices,
their wages
have been declining, and
at the same time, even
interest rates have been going
up. So
if they wanted to
borrow money and
try
to finance themselves,
as we've seen in
past cycles when
rates have been falling, now
we have a depletion of
savings. I
mean, they're
literally doing
everything they can to
hold on. And
the problem is,
the economy is
not really supporting them. So
when we try to
figure out whether this
mini-cycle is just a mini
-cycle or the start of a
trend? You start to
think, "Maybe this is the
start of a
trend," and that
really started to
show up in the
University of Michigan sentiment survey, which
jumped up as if the data
was saying, "Hey, everything's
okay." And then all
of a sudden it's
just  fell. And as you
know, Jeff, where
sentiment goes,
spending often goes
.
Yeah,
the University of Michigan, the latest
preliminary data for
August. And they
said that yes, it was
somewhat
consistent with the contours of the
energy shock,
where oil prices had
previously fallen sharply and
then recovered a little bit
on
optimism about the
Iran conflict
. Maybe a deal
will be made.
Oil prices have come down, although
gasoline prices,
which are worth talking about,
haven't come down much. They've
come off their
highs, but they're
still
painfully high. So
consumer sentiment has kind of bottomed out a little bit
. And I know
you mentioned
that earlier, Steve. It has
n't really
come up much, given that the
oil prices that
many
were counting on and
the optimism about the
Iran conflict
haven't had the expected
effect. So, you know
, consumer sentiment
remains
depressed even
in times of positive
shifts. And then the
preliminary data for
August comes out, along with
weak
retail sales
in July and negative
wage growth in
July. The one thing
we haven't mentioned, at least on this
program,
is the
household survey, which
has been a complete
disaster over the last
few months,
indicating perhaps
even a significant
deterioration in the
labor market, akin
to a recession. Certainly
, the labor force.
The connection to the labor
force here is just
beyond
any perception or
expectation. People are
dropping out of the labor
force, which means
they feel the
economy is bad, and they're not
just telling
some
surveyor about it, they're
actually quitting their
jobs. They're actually
taking action, which means, "We
don't believe
the economy is going
in the right
direction." We
actually think
it's going in the wrong
direction, which is why
we're not working anymore
. So you put all of
these things together.
Gasoline consumption,
sentiment. Right now,
sentiment  are
falling again. Why did sentiment
go down? Because
consumers said, "
We don't like the
state of the labor market, and
we don't like
where it's going." So,
yeah, I mean, you
get to a point
where all these things that
we know about the mini
-cycle happening
have been telling us
to expect a payback in
the summer. So the
real question is
, what does
that payback actually look like?
Is it going to be another
mini-cycle like
last year, where there
were only a few
job losses?
Everyone kind of shrugged their
shoulders, which is obviously
not good for
the economy and not good
for workers, but
for most people
it was like, "Okay,
we got
negative
payrolls."  Who
cares?  "
We've had more
negative
payroll numbers this year,
but we're in a worse
situation. As you
said, Steve, the
comparisons are much
worse in 2026
compared to 2025. So
you really
have to
wonder if there's going to be a
time when everything
starts to fall apart.
Well, Jeff, do you
think that's the
same time? And it looks like that's
because
consumers have been fed a little bit of
stimulus here and there.
They were given some hope
that maybe the conflict
in Iran would end,
and now it's not. It is,
or at least it doesn't
seem like it's going to
end anytime soon
.
They were hoping that
gasoline prices
would come down, but the
oil spread said that was
n't going to happen. And
now as we
look at the world, what are
we starting to see in the
news? There's a
diesel shortage.
So of course what are
the refiners doing?
They're saying, 'Hey, we
can make a ton of
money if we
prioritize
diesel production, and
that means we  "
We're going to produce
more diesel than
gasoline." So when
consumers look
at that, you know, they
saw the light at the end of the
tunnel. And that's why I
think spending went up
. I mean, it
wasn't just
an anticipation of, of course,
higher prices. I think
they had some hope.
And we saw that in the
sentiment surveys
. So why is everything
going down?
Because the conflict isn't
ending,
gas prices aren't coming down,
wages aren't going up.
And, as you
said, people
are leaving the
labor market. So if
you have a job and your
friend loses their job, and you
talk to them, do
you learn anything?
That there are
no opportunities. And when you
start hearing that,
you come home, you
open your
online bank account, you look at your
savings and you think,
"Oh my, if I lose my
job and I'm in my
friend's shoes, I can't
get back into the
labor market." So what are we
starting to see? The
first signs that
people are cutting back
spending. And I think in
the coming months
we're going to see
savings rates rise and
retail sales fall further. I
don't think
consumers
have anything to
look forward to right now
. No more
windfalls, Jeff. I
think that's where the
risk lies.
At the same time, we look
at the economy and
ask ourselves, "What
can they
look forward to that will make it
better?"  "And I do
n't see anything.
You're sitting here,
looking at the situation
, let's go
through the points. What are the
positives in
the economy? The answer
is, as you said,
it's not broken, so it
should be fine. That's
the same 'positive
' point, and on the
negative side,
savings are depleted. You're
absolutely right.
Consumers thought there was
light at the end of
the tunnel because of the
gas price shock, and now
they're like, '
Okay, maybe we
should prepare
better because this doesn't look like it's going
to go away.'" That's the whole
point of the
retail sales report:
consumers are tightening their
belts because the optimism that
this is
just going to be a couple of
weeks, then a couple of
months, and it's going to be over
, and
we can
wait out a short
period and things will get
better. But
now there's the pressure of
job problems and the
cost of gas,
which is not coming down.
So to
sum up the
negatives:
savings
are depleted,
gas prices are not coming down.
As you said,
diesel is
leading
indicator, so
energy costs are
not going to
fall anytime soon. Also,
real incomes
are falling. Some
incomes are falling
in nominal
terms. What else do we
have? The
savings rate is already
exhausted. There is no more
stimulus from
Uncle Sam
. The
job market is
getting worse. People
are leaving the
job market en masse. And so,
none of these things are
catastrophic. This doesn't
look like 2008. It does
n't even look like
2001, which was a
mild recession.
But all of these things point
to negative
trends. So, on the
one hand,
the economy seems
stable because it's not
collapsing.
At least, that's what we're
told. And on the other
hand, there are all these
negative factors
that haven't become
critical enough
to be
noticed yet, but they
are there and they are having an
impact. So, again
, it's a balance of
probabilities. And this
balance is not in favor of
the economy
suddenly, you know,
getting back on its feet and  will start
its journey to a rapid
recovery,
right, Steve?
No, not at all. I
mean, look at the
manufacturing sector. What have
we heard over the last
few months? That
they are building up
inventories. And why are they
doing that? To
keep up with the
price increases. But then suddenly it
turns out that nobody
was factoring in the fact
that
consumers are going to stop spending
. And that's where the
risk lies,
because consumers are saying, "
Look, we're going to have to
stop
spending because we don't have any
more money."
Yes, they could
deplete their
savings even more, but there
comes a point where
people say, "Enough is enough
." And
what we're seeing is that
the accumulation of inventories
turns into a
surplus of inventories. The first thing
we're going to see, and this is what
everyone should be
watching for, is not that
average
hourly wages
continue to fall.
They will fall. The
next thing you're
going to see is that the
hours worked are reduced. And that will be a
leading
indicator that as
demand continues to fall,
employers are going to  say, "
Look, I can
keep
cutting your
hours." Nobody's going to
like that. Or I
can start
getting rid of my
worst
employees and
give priority
to the ones I want to
keep because I
need their
skills, because we
keep hearing from
employers, "I can't
find the
skilled
workers." Well, at
this point in the cycle, you're
not going to lay them off,
but you're going to cut their
hours and lay off
other people. And again
, it's all the same stuff
that we see in
these typical, you know,
late-
cycle events.
Inventory build-up, weak
payrolls, high
interest rates,
high inflation. And in
that case, while
inflation may
come down, I think,
Jeff, because of the
demand factor, it's those energy costs that
consumers ca
n't really do anything about
. I don't think
it's going to come
down much.
Well, that's what disinflation is
, right?
Energy costs remain
painfully high. And
yes, there are some changes in the
metrics.  The CPI, which,
you know, falls into the
CPI itself, but
overall
energy costs are higher than
incomes can sustain. So what's
happening?
Consumers are cutting back on
spending in other
areas. That's what
the CPI and the CPI have been telling us for
the last couple of
months. Instead of
showing what
economists call
second-
order effects, where higher
gas and
energy prices cause,
for example,
service providers to raise their
prices. We haven't
seen that. We've seen the
opposite. So
gas prices have gone up
, and we consumers
have said, "We can't
afford gas, let alone
higher
service prices." So
service providers have
either held their prices
up or
lowered them
as much as they
need to. We've
heard that from
retailers
. You know, McDonald's, McDonald's
is saying, "Hey, we've
got to lower our
prices." You know, we're
losing customers.
So in terms of
consumer prices,
producer prices, you don't
see any
evidence of that
at all. But on the other
hand,  You know, one
thing we haven't
talked about in this
video, even though we
talk about it all the time, is what
employers are doing.
Employers
are feeling the pressure just as much as
consumers are,
because think about it from a
business perspective.
Your manufacturing
costs are going up, your
energy costs
are going up, but you can't
pass those
costs on to your
customers. What are you
going to do?
Where do you think
these
negative
wage reports are coming from? They're coming from
businesses, not, you know,
from the giants, like, you
know, the
tech
giants that we're
talking about, you know,
the hyperscalers that are
caught up in the
AI ​​bubble.
These are small and medium-sized
businesses that are suffering
from the rising costs
of manufacturing. What are
they going to
do? They're doing
exactly what we've seen
all along—cutting
labor costs because that's the only thing they
can control.
Eventually, it gets
to a point where both
consumers and businesses
are saying this is not a
short-term thing. This is
not a mini-cycle. You're
right, Steve.  This is not a
mini-cycle. It doesn't look like it's going to go
away anytime soon
. It's
not going to get better anytime soon. So what
everyone calls a
sustainable economy is
actually incredibly
fragile, and there's a
tipping point where
everyone says, enough is enough. They
have to tighten their belts,
and they're tightening their
belts at the same time.
Now
the question we're asking is: Are
retail sales
a signal that this has
already happened, or is this
just the beginning of a process
that's leading in that
direction? But
either way, this is not a
sustainable economy.
The data clearly
shows that this thing is
fragile, and so the risks are
much higher than people
realize.